okay we're going to start with the
meditation so please get ready
relax your fingers and your shoulders
and your eyelids and the corners of your
mouth
check your spine are you sitting
straight did you reach a place a balance
in your posture
did you turn your cell phone off
and pull in your stomach slightly
and slowly come to your breath today
let's try to count to ten breath without
thinking about something else so
beginning with the exhale try to focus
on your breath count ten rounds of
exhaling into India without thinking
about something else if you think about
something else then gently start over
you
then we're just beginning the month of
May and tomorrow will be many of us will
be going home and I'd like you to think
about some thing you'd like to achieve
during the month of May in your own life
some something like to see happen during
this month of me some change in your
life some nice thing that you have in
mind something maybe you've been working
on I think in my case that there's a
fundraising project we've been working
on think about some goal that you have
in May it could be with your health it
could be a relationship with someone
could be with your work could be with
your meditation it could be something
with how you serve people
then in every task turn two components
one is emptiness and one is comma and
sometimes we call it the marriage of
emptiness and karma and if we cover both
of them then we can be successful so
first let's look at the emptiness of
this task this goal in my case this
fundraising project then emptiness means
the emptiness of something which was not
there something which came from its own
side and in the case of my project it
would be the emptiness of all the things
I would do to reach my goal that don't
involve helping someone else to reach a
similar goal so strategies plans methods
of succeeding that don't involve helping
someone else succeed in a similar
undertaking so
in my case it would be worrying about
you know should I approach the sponsor
indirectly or should I wait a while
[Music]
should I be patient or should I push or
you know should I make long proposals or
should I just use pictures so try to
think of Gaga's try to think of things
that you would normally try to get your
goal to reach your goal which don't
involve focusing on helping someone else
achieve a similar goal think of all
these self existent strategies you might
choice methods and just cancel them one
by one those are not going to work by
themselves it's if I plant deeper seeds
the causes behind the causes then maybe
a proposal with pictures will work
a long detailed written proposal would
work but by themselves neither one's
going to work so cancelled of ideas you
had of the normal things you try to make
things happen to reach your goal
that's emptiness
you
now let's look at karma the brother of
emptiness and this is just the four
steps of master possible Duke what are
the four steps I could use to plant
seeds in my case maybe helping someone
else with their fundraising and then
being sure to rejoice afterwards then I
was planting seeds instead of wishing
things that don't work
so make a decision then to reach your
goal in the month of May you'll try the
4th down since death that doesn't mean
you might not make other decisions about
what kind of proposal or how you talk to
your sponsor financial decisions but now
they have power now they have seats
behind them in the case of your health
you might still of course go to a doctor
and seek one treatment or another but at
the seeds are there the treatment will
be effective and if not the same
treatment won't and if the seeds are
there an alternative treatment will also
work
now we're going to go deeper following
the diamond cutter Sutra where we are
now
Buddha says examine your understanding
of emptiness how strong is your
understanding that methods strategies
plans undertaken without seeds can't
work and how strong is your
understanding of seeds that if you do do
the four steps to almost any strategy
well any strategy we were so examined
may be the relative strength of your
understanding of emptiness how well do
you understand that
normal strategies normal methods can't
work without seeds and that's your
understanding of emptiness and compare
it to your understanding of seeds how
strong is your understanding of the real
causes and how to plant those real
causes
how does your understanding of emptiness
compared to your understanding of
dependent origination of seeds are they
both strong are they equally strong
and now the final part of this
meditation what are the seats for those
understandings what can I do to have
stronger understandings stronger faith
and that comes from sharing as much as
you understand with other people if I
share as much as I understand with other
people who really want to know not
bothering people who don't want to know
if I share then I will have a stronger
faith and habit of using seeds I'm
thinking about seeds and emptiness so
what can I do in May to plant the seeds
to have this strong understanding that I
should plant seeds for my goal what
plans do I have for sharing what I've
learned
with people who want to know so I can
have stronger habit of understanding
that without seeds strategies don't work
and wood seeds any strategy will work
what are my plans for sharing and of
course the best method of sharing is by
example not so much by talking talking's
good if I'm an example of what I advise
other people to do
and it's always nice to check back in
with your heart teacher whoever that may
be deep within your heart in a tiny
space that's private just for your
teacher
in three long exhale to send the good
karma of this meditation to help this
world and then you can open your eyes
relax take stress
[Music]
that's meditation 11 it's called not
staying and nothing and staying in
nothing favor attachment to the two
great ideas what are the two great ideas
yeah combine emptiness thank you where
this meditation comes from is section 80
okay in this Sutra I'll try to give you
the section numbers venerable Jigme I
pointed out that I've been I haven't
been giving you the section number so
you don't know where I am in the suture
today you should get the sutras fall
Sutra any moment it went it went to
taste on and came back okay so you're
going to get the whole Sutra and I'd
like to thank Nick for arranging that
[Applause]
[Music]
speaking of fundraising mr. Dunn you got
to give me a list for a squeezing list
for after the break
okay here's what the Buddha said but
it's offer to our Great Beings give up
every kind of conception and they
develop it in themselves to wish to
achieve perfect and total enlightenment
and they developed this wish within them
without staying in any of the things
that you see Noren sounds more and
smells norm tastes nine things you can
touch nor in any object of the thought
at all then who says neither did they
develop delish Mills body generate
within them by staying in what these
objects lack what that means emptiness
so they don't even stay in emptiness
okay they don't stay in their
understanding emptiness obviously they
don't stay let's take it back to the
husband who's yelling at you okay if you
yell at your husband the first day after
this retreat you really had a bad
retreat okay second days okay okay
remember we got it ready first day it
means that you didn't do anything okay
all right so you can one one trap is
that when the husband yells at you you
you believe it okay like you you fall
for it he decided to yell at me this has
nothing to do with how I'm treating
other people okay
that means you got trapped in
self-existence okay then but maybe you
catch yourself okay
and you say wait I just attended you
know like 10-15 days of retreat and and
now all I'm supposed to remember
there's no husband coming from his own
side that's emptiness right and then you
have to remember that you're remembering
it's also empty okay but you gotta
remember that you need to keep planting
seeds to remember there's a famous story
of a king in ancient India and and the
Prime Minister came to the king in Santa
there's a terrible problem and he said
what and they said this plant is growing
in the water supply and it's a poison
and it's gonna make everybody crazy
everybody in the whole country will
become crazy you know then the kings
that will make sure that I have clean
water I don't want to go crazy
I have to stay not crazy and the
ministers I'm sorry you know you have to
drink water we don't have any water that
doesn't have this plant you know so the
king he had a sharpie and he he made a
mark on his head a big X you know and he
said when I see them marks I will
remember that I am crazy he made a mark
on his head then like a week later he's
in front of the mirror brushing his
teeth what's that mark in my hand
you couldn't remember okay so on the
second day your husband yells at you and
you start to forget what you learned in
between try to remember how you can
remember the emptiness of remembering
okay and that that is sharing what you
learn with other people okay so I'm sure
everybody on the plane to Singapore
Guangzhou we will teach the person
sitting next to you who is yelling at
their husband okay
all right like share it share it with
somebody you don't have to say you're a
Buddhist nobody cares
okay just say you know I heard this
thing like seems to me if your husband's
yelling at you it might be connected to
yelling at your kids or something just
you don't have to say it came from
diamond cutter Sutra and this is come
last year loud 750 ad same time run time
and you ain't a teacher and you don't
have to bore them okay
like I bore you okay so that's the
emptiness of understanding emptiness
okay and that's the emptiness of
remembering to use it and and if you
forget it
then you are staying in emptiness
staying in the diamond cutter Sutra
means you'd think it's self existent
you think it's coming from its own side
even your understanding even you're
remembering has to have its own seeds
okay so
- pretty simple one by the way not to
come unless you know says say goodbye to
all your wrong ideas even about your
wrong ideas okay say goodbye so that's
the photograph that guy's not coming
home he's leaving okay
he's got lunch in his hand okay I tried
really hard to find a picture of
somebody saying goodbye to their wives
and going to work you know so he's
moving those ideas he said say goodbye
to those wrong ideas okay that's the
idea he's not coming home okay don't
forget next one by the way we're on
schedule and very unusual let's see if
we can get off schedule
now that I'm going to go to section 83
and again you should have beer reading
by the end of this class I'll just keep
the class going till the reading comes
energy Buddha says why why did so he you
know why is it like that
and he says because the Buddha the
Buddha is somebody who speaks right he
is the one who speaks true he is the one
who speaks precisely what is he is the
one who speaks without error exactly
what is so he says four different things
okay ready
he speaks truth sorry he speaks right he
speaks truth he seeks speaks precisely
and he speaks without boo-boo without
mistake with no mistakes okay so he
repeats four different things
then master Camilla Sheila says
obviously this is referring what's a
famous for
yeah the for ayah truth okay for our
interests all right and these are like
the core of Buddhism they're the core of
the Buddhist early teachings they are
the first teaching here we gave them
they've been mistranslated as Noble
Truths that has nothing to do with noble
the word is I thought right it has it
just means I I am means someone who saw
emptiness directly so nothing to do with
noble noble means even when someone
irritates you you do the right thing but
that's a result of ayah but it's not aa
okay so it's a very poor translation
it's a very misleading translation and
probably should translate the name of
the first teaching that would ever gave
correctly anyway I choose why are you
truth because a person who saw emptiness
directly directly perceives the truth of
these four things okay okay by the way
after they see emptiness directly after
they come out of emptiness directly
while they are still in the same room
while they are still in meditation
posture they understand the fourth truth
okay but they're no longer in the direct
assertion of emptiness because some of
the truths are not emptiness okay all
right
first first are your truth yeah every
every part of normal life is pain okay
if you let things go the way they've
been going your husband's going to keep
yelling at you forever okay don't think
it's like animals all the pain in the
world it is all the pain in the world
but for us it's our husband
yelling at it okay if you don't do
something you will always have trouble
with your husband and that's okay it
doesn't matter how good a person you are
if you don't understand the path you you
will always have some trouble okay first
one what's the second truth
it has a cause okay in house it cause I
I built a house for my llama you know I
I inherited some money from my
grandmother I was wrong I didn't have
any money then my grandmother passed
away and I got a lot of money then I
said I'm gonna build a house for you he
said okay could you build a classroom
also okay then I he had a tiny little
house he had little tiny bedroom and I
built a big house next to it I connected
it to the old house and every year it
would leak the roof would leak where
they were connected you know because
there are different ages ones moving
ones not moving and we would find water
in the bathroom or we will find water in
the kitchen and if you ever had a leaky
roof it leaks over here and then it
travels over there and then you don't
know where's the lid so Sun fires like
that okay you have to find whereisdan
me okay it's not enough to clean up the
water over here it's not going to fix it
you see then a water will leak in
somewhere else because the real leak is
over here so second truth second ayah
truth find the real source of the leak
source of trouble what's really causing
the trouble with your husband okay
what's the rule cost for him to
criticize you okay you have to find it
okay
it's not enough to say oh honey I'll
make you a good dinner you know don't
don't yell at me okay that's not going
to fix it that's like cleaning up the
water over here you didn't you didn't
fix the source of the problem
okay so that's the second ayah truth is
the source by the way in the diamond
cutter Sutra section 83 Nicole you have
good news for us
well let's pass it out it means or you
could just keep in the bug we had some
sponsors they want to be anonymous let's
give her my hand I would like one i'll
find three mistakes the first night
opening hey the pictures gone on the
front
cool there are four great languages of
the diamond cutter sutra the first was
Sanskrit second is Chinese
third is Tibetan fourth is English
now those Russkies not a robot admired
and are part of a deep produce and
German we need German we need Spanish
okay Monica
[Applause]
okay so you can go to number 83 I hope
it's correct yeah there's the guy okay
everybody have section 83 page 19 when
you translate it keep the section
numbers okay then we're always on the
same page yeah she just wants a copy
she's not asking a question what tell
here Gelf a neat one
over here we need more or you can take
mine here I'm okay I got it on my
confuse err
all right then okay 83 now when the
Buddha says Buddha says to savuti Buddha
speak right what's he talking about
yeah your husband that yelling husband
okay got it
jutice suffering thanks he speaks true
what's he talking about
yeah the cause of the yelling husband
you yelled at your kids last week you
yelled at your kids left me now the
third sentence he says precisely what's
correct he says exactly what's going
which one is that third truth and of
pain okay the truth of the end of pain
normally the four truths are presented
result calls result costs sometimes
they're presented cause result calls
result which is confusing but here it's
result cause result cost okay
life is pain there's a reason you can
get out there's a path okay so forth
truth time which is what he describes
without error
okay got it so he's described that and
then people say you know people in
university say oh you know Buddha what
must have had a bad day he didn't have
his coffee and he just repeating himself
okay he's not repeating himself he has a
reason there's always a reason in the
diamond cutter Sutra why dude every
teach himself
it's called dip it dip it can those of
you who are translators classical fault
of composition to repeat yourself
unnecessarily redundancy and and Buddha
doesn't have this problem
okay all right now I'll tell you what
master commercial excessive on it he
says this verse is this this part is
describing the fact that Buddha is a
semi Keable ya pramana save hamana
hamana hamana hamana means you saw
correctly saw correctly okay and there
are whole books about Pomona what's the
most famous one Vermont of arctica Ramon
of article written by Dharma Kitty okay
Dharma kitty about 1500 years ago okay
logic Buddhist logic okay people hate
the word logic but in this section we
got to get logical okay
so master Dharma here these big
achievement was to write a book about
Pomona correct perception correct
perception okay how many of our normal
perceptions are Pomona you can say
99.9999% okay like if you if it's
getting dark and you see at least going
across the road in the wind and you slam
on your car brakes you know that's
that's a not per mama
that's a mistaken perception you know
your husband is texting somebody and
he's smiling and you know because you're
jealous you you have an on Pomona oh
he's got a girlfriend then you check his
phone and it's he's ordering your
birthday gift on on
okay so that's called a non-permanent
under under the influence of drugs
alcohol tiredness jealousy you can have
non-pom on us okay
some husbands aren't cheating on you so
be careful okay but that's a non pomona
but 99% of your perceptions are pramana
okay how many of the perceptions you
have when you ask yourself why is my
husband yelling at me are correct in
Buddhism we say almost zero okay when
you think about you know how am I gonna
reach my goal in name my fundraising
goal how will it happen when you ask how
then about 99 percent your perceptions
are mistaken okay all the strategies you
come up with all the methods you think
of are self existent you know they're
not going to work without seeds okay and
by the way who came first commercial or
Dharma QT Dharma Quixote by a couple of
hundred years so Kamla sheila was using
gamma Katie's methods okay and
commercially translated or wrote about
20 of the works in the Buddhist Canon in
the collection of Buddhist books he's
very he's written a lot of books and he
also translated a lot of books okay so
he was very familiar with Dharma charity
and he uses Dom acuity and the second
chapter of Dharma character is called
the chapter on proving Ramana
and there's an argument about the order
of the chapters but the second chapter
is what is Pomona what is correct the
section how can you say the Buddha is
correct okay then why should I believe
the bruna okay why should I believe
diamond cutter Sutra okay then in
Buddhism we say you shouldn't believe
what a person says unless you can prove
the person cannot lie okay unless you
can prove the person always says to
correcting you shouldn't believe them
you should not don't believe a book just
because Buddha's spoken and don't
believe a book because it's written in
Sanskrit or Tibetan or ancient Chinese
okay there are many bad books written in
Sanskrit
there are many mistaken books written in
Tibetan okay not everyone who teaches
Tibet Britain knows anything okay so be
careful in China people are if they have
a red robe people are like oh this
person is real Lama you know be careful
you know check what they say okay it's
not the robe it's what they say right be
careful how do you prove someone can't
lie okay and that's the second chapter
of Dhamma carroty how do you prove and
it's ACI course for proof of future life
okay there's a ACI course number 4
called proof how to prove future life
okay and a big part of that proof is to
prove that Buddha cannot lie okay so so
Camila Sheila makes a classical argument
okay classical argument means taking
take a subject like Buddha
say something about the Buddha that
maybe not everybody knows okay and then
prove it with something that everybody
knows okay got it
that's Buddhist logic something number
one pick something or somebody number
two say something about them that people
don't understand yet
number three prove it with something
people already understand okay that's
just Buddhist logic okay you can use it
against your husband I lived with Ken
roberge's for 25 years I lived with my
Lama for 25 years we are like an old
married couple
when we have breakfast it's like this we
know everything the other person better
say then it's hopeless to argue with him
he beat ten thousand debaters on the day
he got his guessing he was number one in
in Lhasa he beat everyone in the three
great monastery to try to argue him it's
impossible he will say this house is
upside down and he will prove it I like
a remedy oh yeah okay so how do I feel
that gives a Buddhist proof okay ready
consider the Buddha okay let's take the
Buddha right the first step of logic you
have to choose something or somebody
what's the subject okay let's talk about
good okay let's talk about Bruner number
two now number two is one something
about Buddha then maybe not everybody
except okay that's called Gupta in logic
it's called the quality to be proven
okay here instead what he says he's
always true okay
what he says is always true okay then
third third part of the logic should be
something about Buddha that we can all
accept already that we already accept
okay which proves number too many and
this relates to how you teach other
people okay
this relates to how you share with other
people and that's why it's here in the
diamond cutter Sutra okay ready
he only talks about what he has seen
himself directly okay he only talks
about what he he doesn't talk about
things he hasn't seen or done got it and
that's why he's a we call a a person of
pramana
he's a Pomona person he's always right
because he only talks about things that
he experienced himself okay why the
picture that I chose took me a long time
to find this particular look I wanted
this particular in look what's she doing
she sees okay she's seeing okay talk
about things you see then you're a
person of Pomona
okay well Buddha silence exactly what I
mean
doesn't have to be directly yeah you
could prove it to yourself indirectly
okay but generally a Buddhist have to be
careful to talk about
things that they have experienced them
some or you can say I I heard it into
teaching or I read it in a book III
didn't experience it myself but this is
what the book says okay that's why it's
so useful to follow a book a scripture
and follow something Buddhist in that's
what we're doing we're going through the
scripture right so generally the best
sharer or teacher is someone who
experienced that thing themselves okay I
want to teach you you're gonna talk to
the person on the plane right let me
teach you about the four steps they're
like did you use the four steps yes how
I used to have a yelling husband now he
makes dinner every night okay he doesn't
have chance to yoga he's busy in the
kitchen okay good Connie John doesn't
yell anyway okay all right so the point
of this part of the Sutra the picture
she sees she sees she talks about what
she sees she tried it okay she's talking
about what she saw okay what she
experienced and that makes you a great
teacher
okay that's why the meditation is called
the logic of truth the fortress speaking
about what you've seen Buddha is a
person of Pomona Britta is a person who
speaks the truth
right why because he only talks about
what he's experienced himself he tried
it okay he tried it now he's teaching it
okay got it
alright then master , Sheila makes a
joke
he says anyway
someone who talks about the fortress
must be telling the truth because the
fortress reveal the big line someone who
talks about the for truth is is showing
the big lie what's the big lie your
husband comes from his own son okay
that's the big lie
looks like he decided together you but
he didn't he had to yell at you he had
no choice even if he says I don't want
to yell here we go why you forced him
how you know that your kids last week
okay got him what's the big line your
husband was the other here that's a big
line he doesn't want to yell at you you
forced him he didn't have choice maybe
he doesn't even perceive he's yelling
how many times somebody said to you
don't yell at me Mom like I did I didn't
know I was just asking you to wash the
dishes
I asked you very in a very soft voice no
you yelling at me maybe he doesn't even
perceive he's yelling maybe you perceive
me okay so the idea that he's yelling
from his own son is a good line anyone
who talks about that line
anyone who realizes it's a lie must be
telling the truth
like commonly she listens done okay
anyone who says it's not true it's not
coming from him already they broke the
big line okay got it all right he
master Kamla Sheela can't let it go he
wants to go deeper do you all right
he can't stop there he made a nice point
everything's okay we understand
I shouldn't teach things I didn't
experience myself or if I do I should
make it clear to my students I'm
teaching you about this but I didn't
reach it myself
I'm trying okay be honest with your
students okay
the biggest lie possible in Buddhism is
to lie about what you experienced oh I
was talking to my jury yesterday I made
off all came for breakfast you know
that's the worst lie in Buddhism you can
lie about you know how much money you
have that's okay but don't lie about
your spiritual life be honest with your
students okay
I'm teaching you how to deal with people
who yell at you but I have trouble
myself when people yell at me okay to be
honest okay do I use it perfectly no do
I understand it mostly be honest with
your students they can smell it by the
way every student can smell it okay you
can't line your students okay the first
time you claim to be perfect they're
going to see you get upset at somebody
then you have double trouble you got
upset and you your students found out
you were lying just say I'm trying
really hard I made a lot of progress I
use the four steps sometimes and when I
do I get great results but I don't
always remember to use them and just be
honest okay people can smell it people
will follow you more if you're honest
about your weaknesses then if you try to
be on perfect teacher okay all right
okay okay so classic our machine is not
satisfied he wants to go back to
disembodied karma triggers atoms like I
remember done i'll give five dollars
american not singapore it's more not
right not sure to anyone who can tell me
what's the disembodied karma triggers in
this section number 83 and i'm gonna
have a coffee because you all be able to
tell me quickly
huh come on say it slower I had to enjoy
a coffee Luca she's right she said how
does truth of how does the second truth
cause the first truth if they never
touch okay
I yell at my kids my husband yells at me
how did how to stack
how does yelling at the kids cause the
husband to yell at me three days later
okay but it's like a concurrent yeah
it's like a cocoon you're right but
don't tell everybody the answers right
away that's part of teaching she's right
yeah so he mastered kumla Sheila points
out there's to cause and effect change
going on in the fortress okay yelling at
your kids which is truth number two
cause this truth number one which is
your husband yelling at you okay truth
number three is your husband washes
dishes and cook instead of yelling
it's called cessation okay that's two
done with me okay got it and chase
number four is the path choose number
for some time what's the path stop
yelling at your kids right follow the
path stop yelling
if you don't like people yelling at you
that's the park the park if you're from
British Columbia which is a bhoot okay
that's the path got it okay how can the
path
trigger the husband washing dishes and
cooking instead of yelling how can it
trigger it it never touches it you stop
yelling at your kids on Thursday your
husband stops yelling on Saturday
where's the connection by the time
you're done not yelling at your kids
they're gone that that that day is
finished then the next day your husband
starts washing dishes instead of yelling
then how can there be a connection you
know they cannot touch each other okay
yelling at your kids has to finish
before your husband yells at you so they
can't interact
one of them has left the room already
okay how can they touch each other the
seed never touches the tree who made the
connection yeah that's also coming from
you that's also coming from you okay got
it all right so now you were really deep
with master combination okay the
impossible connection between cause and
effect it's created by you okay what
let's do one more and we'll take a
bathroom break
I had watermelon juice this morning and
we're going to speed up speed up this
verse here
oh that's not going to go very easy okay
all right now in the next photo I tried
really hard to find this photo I
remembered it or a similar photo and
it's 13 it just reminds me of the middle
way on the left there's a bunch of trees
on the right there's a bunch of trees
and we're trying to go down the middle
way okay so this photo is about middle
way okay and the verse by Lord Buddha
you ready I'm going to read from it's so
nice to have the reading I'm sorry I
didn't get it to you earlier section 84
section 84 and I speak to you further of
the booty of that thing where those God
does with some absolutely total
enlightenment and I split you of that
thing which is a dharma that they teach
it is not true and it is not a lie okay
the Dharma that the Buddha teaches is
not true and it's not a lie deception
means lies okay deception okay and and
Carla Sheila gets all except excited oh
this is middle way this is the meaning
in the minimum way okay got it
that's why you have this photo so
remember the photo okay a middle way
between truth and deception does that
mean I shouldn't try to be true
no okay what's the third line is saying
the meditation not what it sounds like
okay it doesn't mean you have don't use
truth or don't risk destruction choose
something else it doesn't mean that okay
it means
in one way what the Buddha taught was
true and in another way it was not true
ok but don't think he's a liar on
Wednesday he lies on Thursday he tells
the truth it doesn't mean that not what
it sounds like ok we're going to talk
about this section 84 right in two
different ways one is ultimate and one
is not ultimate one is ultimate and one
is not ultimate why did the booty cry
during the Sutra he said you never say
anything without talking about ultimate
well maybe he's crying because he
doesn't understand it I don't know there
are two kinds of crying in the room
maybe one person can cry both ways
this is cold I don't understand okay so
first comma Sheila's careful he says I'm
going to tell you one meaning of section
84 but it's not the ultimate meaning
it's just an interesting meaning okay
ready and this gets into a subject of a
CI course 15 which is called tongue a
tongue a we talked about it a little bit
sometimes Buddha said what he really
wanted to say and sometimes he said
something lower than what he really
wanted to say why the students weren't
ready the students weren't ready okay
kiss ah this doesn't sound like DC I
thought I know that's for the lower
students to tell you the truth okay it
has a lot of big stuff in it
but mostly it's like oh you can make
more money okay that's not what I really
want to talk about but if I talk about
what I really want to talk about 20
people come if I talk about money 2,000
people come so so that's Kesha Michael
only want to talk about money
no just talk about money if he has to
talk about money to get people to come
to listen to the higher stuff okay so if
everything getting Michael say true in
that sense no no you know is the main
thing money no why you say that in DC I
number one because that's the audience
okay got it
so from that point of view which is not
an ultimate point of view we are not
discussing ultimately real ultimately
unreal we're not talking about time even
from normal point of view some of what
Buddha said is not exactly true it's not
exactly what he want to talk about okay
and that's a big subject in Buddhism and
I told you about it before there were
three periods in the teaching career of
the Buddha there were three great
periods in the long career we are lucky
Jesus died when he was 30 he was killed
when he was 30 we have we have about 30
pages of of Christian real real word of
Jesus we have 30 pages Buddha we have
also still we have a hundred two hundred
thousand pages okay we still have and
most of it's locked
okay so he lived to 81 he taught for a
long time over 50 years and he talked a
lot so we still have here
we are lucky so there are three great
periods what are they called
yeah three turnings of the way on three
turnings of the wheel in the first
turning of the wheel Buddha seemed to
say most things come from their own son
yelling husband come from his own son
and you just have to learn to deal with
him that was first period in his career
teaching during the second period of his
career he said nothing comes from us on
sight
nothing about your husband coming from
him not the sound not the red face not
the words not the movements not the
feelings all coming from you okay
nothing comes from his son okay second
turning of the wheel after the secretary
of the wheel I guess there was a lot of
complaints on the internet now Buddha
crazy you know nothing exists nothing
come from its own sign then Buddha
thought oh I better soften it I better
you know make people feel good then in
the 13 in the wheel he said you know
that secretary real I don't know I just
I guess I didn't have enough sleep that
night I was just got to radical you know
of course some stuff comes from their
own time the top of the pan the bottom
of the pan they're out there then then
then your karma opens because you shared
tense in the past and it makes a 10 but
of course there's this thing out there I
didn't say that the pieces aren't there
I didn't say none okay and he taught
mine only school and in lower lower
middle way okay third turning of the
wheel okay then many people noticed and
it really bothered some copper two of
them have to be wrong
two of the three turning of the wheel
has to be wrong only one can be correct
okay he decided the gardener decided
Buddha decided it's number two is
correct okay that means number one and
number three are false okay so there is
truth in Buddhism and there is deception
in Buddhism but benign deception let's
talk about money okay it's not trying to
hurt those people
we're just trying to get them higher
okay trying to hook them and get them
higher okay all right so it's it's not
exactly true the money is so important
but it's if you talk about it more
people will come and then they can learn
higher things okay by the way my name is
called - Maureen modem - monkey mojo
yeah shared you don't give it up when
you become Buddha and you still have a
paradise you don't give up your
mercedes-benz you just take it with you
okay it's a higher the higher thing but
you don't give up the lower thing you
can have that also you have born okay
all right okay so in that sense some of
what Buddha said is true and some of
what he said is not exactly true so you
can say it's okay to say the Dharma that
the Buddha taught was neither true nor
false the total Dharma that Buddha
taught was neither hundred percent true
or 100 percent false okay
somewhere between middle way okay that's
not the ultimate meaning of section 84
it's just something good to know okay
what's the ultimate meaning of section
84 I'm glad you asked
oh by the way to go back to that last
idea commonly Sheila says this is drunk
dog to think everything to think that
everything the Buddha said was true or
literal is don't dog with that over
raining overrating okay in a non
ultimate way to think everything Buddha
said is true is to overrate it's not
there but you put it there okay it's not
correct but you you make it correct in
the husband example what is overrating
there's a husband there who's coming
from its own son okay there is no such
thing but you put it there you make it
you make a husband like that
but there's no such husband like that
okay in buddhism we call overrating
overrating what's underrating Oh
everything's illusion there's no husband
in the kitchen I don't have to cook
tonight okay middle way means between
those two okay don't think that husband
come from his own side and don't think
there's no husband enough there is a
husband coming from you middle way
that's middle way and that we have a
very cool project we're working on the
Buddha after the surgery of the wheel
people got so confused they said which
which one was true Lord Buddha you know
and then he taught a Sutra called Sunday
near mo China Sutra what I really meant
what I really meant in the 6th chapter
he gets a question from a bodhisattva
called Parramatta woodcutter and he the
Bodhisattva says come on what did you
really mean which one was true
Buddha get an answer are you you ought
to go deeper in that answer he says
number three was true cuz the audience
because of the iron okay
then people like their garden and they
said well he really means number two so
you have to interpret what the Buddha
said about interpret that's very subtle
okay and then that Sutra came to China
it was translated into Chinese it's
missing in Sanskrit we don't have this
sounds good
the Chinese is the oldest version that
we have and master chuan song translated
and he stood in you until you answer yes
sir he wrote a beautiful commentary and
it's two thousand pages and it's part of
the Tibetans liked it so much they
translate it into Tibetan and they put
it in the Buddhist Canon it's part of
the Tibet books it's it's two and a half
big books in the tenure in the Canon
okay it's it's all that what you mean
Kandra means all the books we have from
India that Buddha spoke tango means all
the books we have from India that are
commentaries except you're on says
commentary got in because it's so cool
they took it from China okay so the only
copy now a complete copy commentary
about this subject is in Tibetan yeah
yeah
because now how did people read that
Sutra did they take it literally or not
you want to go deeper
you sure lots of people who wrote about
that Sutra said you know I support what
the gardener said about the center so
the gardener said Buddha means the
second turning was crying okay and then
there came lots of people later who said
I grooves in the gardener and the
gardener said Buddha said number three
was crying with it
oh yeah there's lots of clues now no no
no no maybe
that chapter is empty and maybe people
with different seeds and see different
things there got it okay that's the big
answer that's the big big answer okay
okay anyway we can go down forever
let's read run test some time together
it'll be fun
that said it's really beautiful I read
some of it and we're going to translate
part of it part of it to translate all
that would take 50 years we're gonna
translate some pieces okay about this
subject yeah yeah you can follow the
Chinese the the important chapter the
sixth chapter about this question
it exists in Chinese yeah according to
Stanley Chen okay I can't say myself but
it'd be cool to teach it like maybe in
some university or something in China
there because all right this case yeah
yeah
all right now I said that wasn't the
ultimate discussion of this part the
ultimate discussion is true means
complements on time true from its own
side
it's the Dharma that Buddha thought so
true that it comes from its own time so
real that a consummate on time then we
say no not like that
that's not what true means okay got it
that's the deeper meaning here okay what
Buddha said is not true in the meaning
that come from its own time okay if you
think that's the meaning of ultimate if
ultimate means that things should come
from its own side then nothing is
ultimate okay got it
well then no no you want to go deeper
you sure okay I like it I can never do
this in DCI program say nun Taeyang tea
sorry no I'm searching I'm searching
some things you have to establish by
canceling what it is not some things you
have to establish by cancelling what
it's not okay what's an example I don't
know changing or unchanging okay what is
you can define unchanging thing as
anything which exists which is not a
changing thing you cut all the changing
things if you take all the things that
exist in the world and you cut cut all
the changing ones what do you have left
I'm changing things that in LA in in
logic that's called noms hij okay cut
you can reach the unchanging ones by
cutting all the changing ones assuming
you have a bag of existing things okay
you have to say that my bag has all the
existing things I'm going to take out
all the changing ones what's left yeah
all the unchanging things so some things
you have to see this way by cunning okay
how do you decide what's false
you cut all the two things what's left
is false guarding you comfortable if
you're comfortable I'm not teaching it
very well okay there's a few comfortable
people here I'll say it again
how do one way to arrive at what's false
is to eliminate what's true and okay
somebody some politician gives a
one-hour talk okay
then take all the facts they mention
take all the ones that are true and
throw them out now what do you have left
all in line no now I'm assuming you know
what I'm assuming you know what's true
okay assuming you know what's true you
you eliminate all the true things he
said and and you understand all the
things he said and you know what's
correct but you cut on the ones he he
said which are true which is what
newspaper people do during the recent
campaign they actually started to count
how many things the person said that was
not correct but they didn't report the
things he said which were correct
because that's not interesting so they
took out all the correct things then
they report everything else look this
was a line this is a line this is
I can account they have a count okay now
we just said nothing's true we didn't
say anything true in the sense that
nothing's ultimate in the sense that it
doesn't come from its own side the
Dharma you hear the teachers say is not
coming from the teachers it's coming
from you okay so in that sense there's
no ultimate thing Geshe Michaels saying
today
there's nothing true true true coming
from me it's all come from you
okay got it so is there anything
ultimate which I'm saying we can say no
aha so nothing's false either why you
get to false by cutting out the truth
but if there's no true you can't cut it
then you can say what some crazy person
said nothing I said was true and nothing
I said was sauce who said that in the
diamond cutter just now Buddha said it
Buddha said it got it
that's a deeper meaning if you
understand that you can go to the toilet
or if you just take it to get to the
toilet okay let's say it one more time
okay if I if the politician talks for an
hour and you take out all the to stuff
they said what you have left is numpce
chi chi right logic principle what you
by the way well anyway take out
everything they said which was true then
what you have left is what to call okay
got it
so to get to deception to get to the
idea of deception in Buddhism you have
to know what's the truth because you
arrive at deception by cutting out truth
okay
but Buddha just said there is no truth
so you can't cut it so there's no
deception either therefore nothing
Buddha said is true and nothing Buddha
said is fun stop okay
that's maybe one of the hardest ones and
we had to do and by the way commonly
Sheila gets very excited he says if you
understand this you understand middle
way if you understand what I just said
you reach the middle way okay now let's
take it to the husband okay let's make
it real from my life you know get LA
that's all philosophy what about my
husband okay
middle way means one extreme he is the
way he seems he is the way he seems it
seems like he's yelling at me because he
decided to yell I mean I didn't do
anything I just came home I opened the
door husband's like look I didn't do
anything that husband is is one extreme
it's the trees on one side you you drive
your car there you will die okay don't
hit the trees on the side left I'm
husband is real husband decide to yell
at me that's one wrong idea oh gosh mom
if there's no husband in my kitchen
could be site here at me then there's no
husband at home then there's no husband
at all that's the only way a husband can
be if there's no husband beside here at
me then there's no husband got it that's
the other trees on the right side that's
the other extreme Buddhist has to go
down the middle middle way what's the
middle way there is a husband but he
come for me there's a new kind of
husband in my house
okay that one will come from me okay why
I planted him when last week how when I
yelled at my kids yeah so a thing that
happened last week and his daughter is
causing your husband now yeah that's
your problem okay
that's a disembodied commentary right
okay all right let's take a pee-pee
break the rest is easier okay I promise
but you didn't come here for easy okay
all right and told asked me a good
question he said when you say section 84
is that the same as master Carla
Sheila's sections no his 18th sections
okay different thing okay and well he
said well what section are we in and I
said you know but I didn't know but
we're still in Section 13 which is not
worrying about hard things in your
practice okay like being able to do hard
things in your practice okay
and we're going to do a section 85 of
the suture which is very beautiful by
the way the section numbers in in your
big book the suture I'm following how
master Kamla Sheila cuts it okay and so
I decided to use that forever it's
different people cut it different ways
but he's the earliest great commentary
we have so maybe that's a good way to
cut it okay okay so number 85 civility
this is how it is think of the example
of a man who has eyes to see but is
sitting in the garden he sees nothing at
all if a bodhisattva falls into things
and then practices the perfection of
giving they are just like this men okay
this man has eyes they're not blind
they're sitting in dark retreat cottage
all the windows are shut
outside sun Arizona Sun bright enough
okay and they have ice but if you
practice sharing your things with other
people if you're generous but you don't
know what you're doing okay you don't
know about these then you are like a man
sitting in a dark room okay and the Sun
is bright outside now I've got a master
Kamla Sheila's commentary what's the
picture here it looks like getting wrong
on Orchard Road on a good day in
Singapore
Singapore's the best place to shop in
the world I don't care there's nothing
like in dinner I like to just I like to
shop there
[Music]
for my friends and things my old lady
for example so it's called a blind man
in a room of riches and and those of you
who are teaching BC I like mr. and mrs.
Vasek this is the verse for you in this
section 85 right commerce ela goes crazy
about the five goals of DCI okay it's
like he just got back from DC i level
one and he says you know if you know
what you're doing if you understand
seeds then you can have a nice life why
not
okay you can have you can be independent
financially he mentions it you can have
a nice relationship you can have good
health he mentions it specifically and
your practice goes well your meditations
go well you serve other people you enjoy
serving other people it's a perfect DCI
commentary right here okay and if you
don't understand how things are coming
from you you are like a man with eyes
sitting in a dark room surrounded by
cool shopping ok many things to that you
could have okay the best dress the best
shoes the best purse is in the room but
you can't see it okay then you're just
unhappy you are sitting in the dark open
the door open the window let us Sun come
in look at all the school stocks you
know
can have a nice house you can have a
good health you can stay young okay
don't sit in the darkroom okay who's
sitting in the darkroom the body sabha
who fell into things of course that
always means who thinks the husband
coming from their own side okay who
doesn't understand sees even Bodhisattva
okay if they tried buried if your body
starter have you seen emptiness directly
not necessarily not necessarily
Bodhisattva someone who wants to help
the whole world DCI goal number five but
they don't know how okay that's called a
bodhisattva whose sunglasses are too
dark okay all right so we're talking
about that kind of body something they
want to practice they want to help
people they want to be generous but they
they don't understand that the money you
use to give away also has to come from
giving okay you can't be generous if you
don't have anything okay you can't
really help people if you don't have
anything okay so it's okay to have money
it's okay to look nice it's okay to have
a comfortable car you know I had an
uncomfortable car jing-mei gave me her
old used car it was stolen by somebody
like ten years ago then the police in
Los Angeles called her we found your car
after three years or something we found
your car it's a really old car you know
this purple volvo volvo right yeah no
air conditioning i used to have two
pairs of clothes one is for driving the
car one is when i get out of the car
I'm totally sweat totally Congress it
used to break every mile you know and
she gave it to me she asked the police
said we're gonna auction it she said
well how much I have to pay they said
it's worth $50 she said I'll take it she
gave it to me okay
then I was just trouble okay you can't
help people if you don't have anything
it's difficult you can't you can't go
somewhere to teach in country okay you
don't have a car you know or your
clothes are all sweaty nobody wants to
learn to you can change from you all
right so Camila Sheila says a
bodhisattva who has eyes who gives
things to other people with eyes meaning
with understanding seeds then even they
will get material and emotional success
stable health and body and of course the
ultimate wealth which is Buddhahood okay
the ultimate wealth and he says if they
don't work on their view of emptiness
they will forfeit what they could have
had they could have had cool things and
they won't get them there like a man
sitting surrounded by beautiful things
golden beautiful things from a car that
has air-conditioning up to Buddhahood
okay they're surrounded by it but they
can't see it okay they will forfeit it
and then he says they will get
discouraged and they will give up giving
they will stop trying to give things to
people because they don't they don't
understand how it works they don't
follow the four steps they try to be a
nice Buddhist but nothing happens so
then they quit okay and that's the worst
problem of not understanding emptiness
is you will quit you will get
discouraged
this is not working I've been generous
how many thousands of people told me
again I've been generous for for 15
years I've visited the old lady for four
five years nothing happened did you do
the four steps yes yes did you do number
four
no no what's number four yeah cafe
mention be be happy the seed will grow
if you're not happy about being nice
okay it won't grow don't complain to me
if you can't do number four most people
have trouble with number four because
we're good people and we don't want to
be proud we don't have to say I'm a good
person but that's okay you have to okay
alright then they will suffer forever
and they will have the third kind of
problem this we were this whole sections
about patience we're still in patience
patience about what was not people who
bother you patients about
inconveniencing yourself for your
practice and then the bigger kind of
patience which is about samsara okay all
right and income lucky letters and
Buddha says the next section says let me
read it for you
this is section 86 and now it's a booty
I think of this man a man with eyes to
see as dawn breaks and the Sun rises
into the sky think how he then sees a
whole variety of different forms this is
a bodhisattva who understands what
they're doing when they give two things
to people okay then
master Kamla Sheila says you can read it
two ways number one The Sun has always
been out that the opportunity of wisdom
is always there okay it's like you're
sitting in a dark retreat cottage at
Diamond Mountain but the Sun has always
been there outside okay wisdom has
always been available you didn't get it
you didn't take it okay or he says you
can think that the Sun came up
you know the guy was sitting at three
o'clock in the morning in his retreat
cottage and then the Sun came up and he
said I like that one because it it you
get the feeling of a war between light
and darkness okay it's a war okay he
says I like the sunrise one you know
it's dark dark dark dark dark in your
life the Sun starts to come up and you
start the war
it's called Dharma okay all right then
it's a war okay when you go home and you
have jet lag and your husband says
you're stupid for going to die mom then
because you're tired you'll forget and
you'll get upset half an hour later in
the bathroom you will remember after he
went to work you did I mean it's too
late but you'll remember it's a war okay
remembering emptiness is a war it
doesn't happen in one day you don't win
this war in one day it took you a
billion billion years to to mess up
don't think you're going to change it in
one retreat okay but I'll tell you this
beautiful thing I told you many times
- a study takes 20 25 years on the last
day last day of the exams they give a
guess he had to everybody
good luck they give every even the
little eight-year-old monks they get a
big - you had to get the haggle and
everybody gets it get your hands they
may hold it and they're waiting you know
actually put it on and then there's the
final question of 25 years it's always
the same question that's how you know
you're almost finished because then the
debate master will ask the last question
you know is there an entertain or not
will will the pain in this world and
some gay that's the question
then you say you know there it will you
willin okay then he says why and you say
when truth meets false truth wins okay
when there's a fight between
understanding your husband and not
understanding your husband's
understanding always wins when when you
just bring up the idea oh I yelled at my
kids I yelled at my kids I yelled at my
kids other my kids okay yeah let me go
ahead he yells at you they say okay then
if you remember the understanding will
always beat the anger okay if you
remember sometimes you remember half an
hour later okay I used to get in fights
at my work and then I go to the men's
room
I have a special meditation toilet I'll
sit in there when I'm upset I don't even
do anything
you know what I mean and I don't think
gee I should have remembered empty
minutes I shouldn't have got in a fight
you know okay so like the Sun when the
Sun comes up the dark has to go forget
it okay if you let the Sun come up
if you struggle to understand that
things are coming from your scenes how
you treated other people okay
it will definitely beat the dark okay it
never happened that the Sun came up and
went back down right away oh it's too
dark
no let's extend come on lych do dark
I'll go back it doesn't happen okay if
you the Sun is your wisdom and the Sun
is understand see then darkness cannot
fight against that Sun not possible okay
all right he likes that one I like that
one
we're almost getting close to nearly
finished for today this is the longest
one because tomorrow it's hard to focus
tomorrow and you can't meditate on it in
retreat okay for Anton cuspid in court
askew we reached
Camilla Sheila's section 14 which is
something you don't know jung-hwa
Daniela means don't get attached to
meditation sensation don't get attached
to the feeling of meditation use it as a
tool but don't get attached to it the
goal is not meditation meditation is
like telescope to see the star but it's
not the star okay it's just a tool don't
get attached to the tool don't spend
your whole life talking about meditation
working on meditation
and ignoring other people okay don't go
and retreat and for the sake of retreat
I'm going to retreat because you want to
use it when you get home okay
don't become one of those people who's
always in retreat and doesn't like
people that that's not the point so the
whole section don't get attached to
retreat don't get attached to meditation
keep in mind you're it's retreat is a
tool for helping the world okay that
that's his that's how he describes this
session okay all right here we go
then it's called the morning time of day
okay this is the most fun meditation
here okay and I'll just give you the
easy introduction and then I'll give you
the hard part okay
here's the easy part there are five
points made in the Sutra which relate to
don't get hung up on your meditation
it's only a tool okay there are five
points about not getting hung up on your
meditation understand that meditation
and retreat our tools for serving others
don't get hung up on the tool and forget
to serve others okay then he's of course
we have to meditate every day but it's a
tool okay
then he says well what happens if you
have that correct understanding you see
meditation is just a tool for you to be
a better mother for you to be a better
husband
for you to be a better business person
what if you succeed and you use
meditation you integrate it into your
real life and serving other people five
cool things will happen to you
five cool things will happen to you okay
number one and this is from the Sutra
and we'll little bit to this five number
one the Buddha's love you did you
dislike looking at you all the time Oh
Vivian so cool look she meditated
quietly at home gym she goes to learn
and she got so cooked God gain you so
cool you know
baba means babe they're just super
attracted to you man that's what I
always wanted a mother a business person
who's using the meditation in their real
life okay they get excited about you
okay that's the first one number two you
make billions and millions of good seeds
okay if you combine meditation with real
life with real service of other people
okay number three we should just all
praise you you know we should all tell
you how cool you are Buddha other
Buddhists if we see a person who is
combining meditation with real life real
service of other people retreat there go
on retreat so then when they come home
they can serve people those people we
should pray you deserve praise okay
we should make song we should make rock
wall song about you know that date you
know we should sing your praises okay
number four naturally all the beings
respect you they honor you you like even
dealers and
and all the tented angels' and other
bodies left us when they see you using
meditation for real life they're like oh
down bow down I bow down to you you even
other body surface other Buddha's they
bow down to you okay number five it it
automatically cleans away your old bad
seats it automatically purifies your old
bad seats if you use your meditation
don't get attached to the meditation
don't get attached to how it Kula feels
use it in real life for your job for
your family for your health okay
then doing that cancels a lot of your
old bad C's okay so keep in mind these
five parts all right now let's go to the
first one I'm going to read you here's
the Sutra okay I'll read it to you for
good luck you don't mind that we're
going on like okay right you didn't want
to do yoga anyway that's why I'm
teaching so long okay
section 88 section 88 ba ba Sabbagh hey
bas abundant and again I say to you
further sebou tea suppose some man or
woman gave away in a single morning time
of day their own body the same number of
times that there are drops of water in
the Ganges River billions and billions
okay and then at midday they did the
same thing and in the evening they did
the same thing
and suppose they did this for billions
and billions of years okay what's he
gonna say next you remember come on
think again
yeah it doesn't compare to the Karma of
Sherrington country it doesn't compare
okay okay that's coming later you know
that but master Kamla Sheela stops here
and I warned you about this part okay he
says oh look he said morning Wow
you know okay he said morning time of
day you get it you get it and they were
all like no he's just talking about
Morton you know then he talks about
Mirren and then he talks about evening I
mean it's okay don't get excited
you know he said whoa no he's talking
about emptyness he's talking about
emptyness what do you mean when he
talking about
why did he use three words when he could
use one why did he say morning time of
day by the way I changed my old
translation because I just said morning
but but okay we're going to go to the
sanskrit so mostly so I can impress you
with this transcript yeah in Tibetan is
not not too too kitteh which means
morning time of day the Sanskrit is
portable Ozma Carla okay blue bus a
pooh-bah Sanskrit doesn't really have a
V they kind of go blip for wa ha
kala okay Karla's easy time right like
color chakra okay elves change two R's
in sanskrit in english so car comes from
that because it's moving it's constantly
moving chariot comes from that
okay acronym means day and board Oba
means early early time of day okay let's
put Walton asana early side what's put a
bolt in us now which asking us that
forward been seated forward bend no huh
oh okay anyway it relates to that
somehow okay anyway morning time of day
okay then okay this is calm less
interesting when when a child is born in
let's say France okay
a child is born in France did you ever
wonder why kids can learn their own
language so fast you know like I tried
to start Chinese 15 years ago some of my
friends had kids during that time those
kids learn Chinese in three years four
years ba ba ba ba ba I'm like still
trying to say me how you know Asians and
the kid is talking Chinese already okay
then is it all people are stupider than
young people no your seeds yeah your
seeds were to be born in China and those
seeds helped you to learn your own
language faster okay because those seeds
created China for you and those seeds
created Chinese language for you and
then some kids have extra seeds like
Stanley okay and they watch a few
American movies and then suddenly
they're talking haggis I do
what's up man you know
okay some people have actresses okay I
don't for Chinese not yet I'm still
trying to wake them up okay so this idea
of learning is a little bit wrong okay
this idea that you are learning a
foreign language it's a little bit wrong
the idea that you recognize a car
because your mom said that's a car honey
it's a mama western mama Jew consumer
then mama said how do you say car sure
whatever
that's a car then you said she said try
to say quoi no car quoi no car car yeah
that's right it's the car okay we call
this car okay mommy
mommy's teaching you actually the whole
learning come from their past life some
kids cannot learn they don't have seeds
the mom said the same thing to two kids
one kid remember one kid doesn't
remember okay so that's how we learn
things
okay now difficult part Buddhism says
the whole world is like white noise okay
English has a word white noise white
noise means like on the plane
you're going to experience it today all
the way to China or Germany or wherever
you're going
just north random noise baby how could
you be you know that's we call white
noise it is not anything specific just
white my whole world
it's like blank white thing everything
there's nothing out there nothing out
there okay there's also no morning time
of day okay there's nothing there's no
time you know in Tibet the time was 60
drops of water from a cup with a hole in
it that's one hour good maybe it's 24
minutes maybe it's 110 it doesn't matter
you see your mind next time from the
white noise okay your mind made morning
time of day okay who decide morning
evening who decide that okay if you live
in my office in New York you divide time
differently there's a work time and
there's coffee break okay your mind cut
the date differently and the second one
is much more important your mind cut the
day differently okay if your mom you
have to pick up your kid at five o'clock
five o'clock is important ten minutes in
the day more important than the rest of
the day you know I can't forget to pick
up my kid the school will call you we
called you ten times already
you're late yo kids the last one he's
waiting here the teachers pissed off
they have to stay because of you so you
learn five o'clock to five ten is
important part of in your mind divided
the day differently then people don't
have kids they don't care if it's five
o'clock okay got it time of day morning
time of day
when the body starts a man or woman give
away their body a billion times it's
random and though you want to go deeper
the word is random the word is random
you could call it evening and you could
call that the evening morning it doesn't
matter
there's nothing about MA or that that
belongs to that time of day there's no
connection
who made the connection good game okay
so come here goes crazy he's so happy
I'm so glad Buddha said morning more oh
I'm so happy that he's talking about
emptiness okay everything coming from me
even the time even time coming from you
okay he gets so excited so don't forget
if you we can have their diamond
mountain jokes kind of cool Diamond
Mountain jokes like tomorrow
no sorry Wednesday Michael will get up
late and Melissa will say good morning
time ago my go then you're gonna pay
emptiness yeah I remember
that's all these diamond diamond
Mountain drugs you know we could do it
in China you know good morning time of
day Jimmy then you're like oh yeah I
remember okay
don't be attached to don't think those
things are coming from themselves
they're coming from you even morning
even Puerto Varas no Ghana is coming
from you then this is what Cebu T was
crying about right not that it was
difficult he's crying about how cool it
is that Buddha doesn't let a single word
come without meaning okay why do you say
morning why didn't he just say they give
their body why he said morning
okay it's cuz it has meaning he's
talking about emptyness
okay alright you want to go deeper there
are no times a day then a silver karmic
seed opens in your mind out of the seed
comes an idea of mourning
okay probably because I you made your
husband get up in the morning too much
or something okay but you have a seat
till morning it opens picture comes out
pen also right this is not a pen yet
it's just a thing then seed comes out of
your mind because you shared tents with
other people in the past and and your
mind cuts a pen out of the white noise
your mind defines pen okay it makes it a
pen out of the white noise okay so some
people like to say you know might mean
bayt.com your mind is labeling things
they say your mind is labeling things
with a name okay but it's deeper than
that your mind is creating things with
name and name means the picture got it
it's not the word pen the real name is
the real name is the picture okay got it
you didn't create this thing with mmm
okay
what do you say John Linda be okay B you
didn't make this thing with me you made
it with a picture okay
so if you what's the real name is that
it's the picture coming out of your skin
okay the world is created by words
the world is created by names but it's
the pictures not the words not the sound
got it okay Tina looks confused I
finally got it if it took me so long to
get confused oh sure it's a very good
question I think so I just wonder if
there is any place in the switcher they
actually used the word picture oh I see
in the suit are just names of yeah names
on something exactly Ming de Ming in
Tibetan Ming day they call it name
picture name picture they say it real
fast name picture okay so really when we
say the world's created by names it's
not created by names if I say 10 it's
not going to make a pen if I share pens
with others put the scene in my mind
picture comes out that's 10
that creates a pen that cuts 10 out of
the nothing out of white noise that cuts
the pin you see it's the same thing but
it's a deep point it's a deep point
yeah good name in language so but in the
end they are both pictures coming out of
your comic seat so don't get confused
when Buddha said name or Buddha said
pictures or name and pictures he meant
coming out of mind
oh sorry name and language means pen
picture not pen word the word cannot
make a pen okay the picture makes a pen
what's the Christian Bible what's the
first word in the Christian Bible yeah
in the beginning was the word that's the
first word of the Christian Bible and
then everybody's like what what does it
mean okay very cool yeah I just mean
opsite you something hang on this is it
really cool basical it's a physical
thing no say that from not not physical
animal
yeah conceptual cutting and let me see I
want to play something you ready I don't
know if it's gonna work they see okay
here we go
listen carefully anyway I was recording
the bird last night there's a British
things at night right it's quiet
steep and it's quieting us deeply I
think it's so cool he's singing at night
everybody else is asleep she's like
really quiet home I don't know four
hours right that beep - is the white
noise the world is just very nothing
then beep beep means morning time day
morning time day is cutting cutting
morning from nothing okay got it
okay alright let me see how much Allah
says I know I know I know
Buddha talked about it before he already
said you can give away your body or you
can cover planets with gold but it's
better karma to read this Sutra and I
know don't think Buddhist dumb people
God he said that already okay there's a
reason why he repeated it you want to
know the reason the last one connected
to the Anton section about not being
attached to outside books
what's the outside book any bad
explanation emptiness could be Buddhist
okay so that's a different subject
this one's talking about not being
attached to Pleasant meditation now you
have to decide why ok that's your
problem I'm not going to explain it last
thing I'll say about this one is those
of you who want to take some day should
take Bodhisattva vows there is a primary
bodhisattva vows in their secondary
bodies nothing else one of the secondary
Bodhisattva vows is what you old Yogi's
tell me yeah yeah exactly
he must be doing this book 94 it's 94
total vows I'm not saying um if you
count all your vows considering the
pleasant sensation of meditation to be
an important personal attainment that's
a breaking about you break about you
break a bodhisattva bow okay
is it bad to have good at meditation no
is it important to have good meditations
yes do you need good meditation yes you
can't see emptiness we're not okay but
don't get a touch to it don't spend all
your time talking about retreat talking
about meditation ignoring other people
okay you know someone really needs you
help them okay
then do your meditation okay that's all
right
the meditation is for helping people
okay all right are you one no let's
freeze children
you want to turn on the air or not no
you feel how many people hot raise your
hand how many people not heart raise
your head okay you win
by the way suction 92 it doesn't have
Sanskrit because the Sanskrit comes
before 91 sorry I didn't want to cut it
up that way so all the sense 492 is in
91 so don't stress out about it okay
we're on meditation 16 what's the
photograph what's the image yeah a dad
is carrying his son on his shoulders
okay let's go to the section 92 section
92 those people who learn the diamond
cutter sutra possess good seeds which
are inconceivable beyond all comparison
cannot be measured beyond all measure
any person who studies diamond cutter
suture let's go to enlightenment okay
dad okay and they're caring here okay
good I promise okay Britta made promise
you study diamond cutter Sutra I'll take
you on my own shoulders to enlightenment
I'll pick you up and and master table
Sheila says don't forget this relates to
the very first part of the answer that
Buddha ever gave to sebou tea in the
beginning sibility said what do you want
me to do what to do to say yeah what did
watch the short answer yes
Nirvana science we got to make a rocket
motor home you've got a new violence
nice people
Nirvana sir take them to Nirvana get
those people to Nirvana that's what I
want
so Buddha talked about taking us on his
shoulders but the meaning is you
to take people on your shoulders okay
that's he's just giving example okay you
have to take people on your shoulders
and on how does that relate to this
section
what's this section yeah don't get
attached to retreat don't get taxed in
meditation use them doesn't mean you
shouldn't do so many no it doesn't mean
that do as many as you have to to carry
people to learn to carry people okay all
right
which reminds me unfortunately for you
our fundraising drive is not quite
finished and me and Michael Dunn we
worked out a new plan it's called the
four it's not the four ayah truce it's a
new form okay the first one is the sound
dampening equipment for the jetsam
copper Center we hang these things from
the ceiling and it gets quiet when you
have a conversation and you don't have
to yell to hear the person next to you
it makes the room more it makes the room
better for quiet conversation even when
there's many people okay that's called
sound dampening system okay that's one
of the four okay got it
then there's three that go together like
the last three truth okay each one of
these is a translation booth okay so we
need four things we need one sound
damping system and we need three more
translation booth we're going to buy the
professional kind which is more
comfortable and you can fold it up and
you can take it to Sedona and you can
use it there okay so a CI can use it
dinah mountain community
okay so there's how many total for each
one costs 10,000 u.s. nope forget it
it's true 9,000 I'm calling it 10 times
it's okay
tax anyway being Michael decided for
James ten thousand dollars each
my suggestion make a team you make a
team okay make four teams like one team
is South China Hong Kong guangzhou
xiangjian one team is Europe you know
Germany Russia okay one is America
Mexico US Canada okay so I'm in the
Americas team I will give two thousand
okay I'll give two thousand we need
eight more okay so you guys make your
own teams okay
my suggestion if you are the person who
gave all the money last time don't give
more make other people again okay one
person gave 80% of the money last time
it's not fair okay we should all share
okay so don't worry you have lots of
time before tomorrow afternoon but I
will give two to the Americas team okay
so let's try to hit ten maybe it takes a
couple of weeks I don't mind okay let's
do it okay just do it okay so what do
you mean money after diamond cutter
Center in case all right you always get
more it'll always come use it while you
haven't if you die in a car with lots of
money man you wasted your money okay all
right hmm then he says something cool he
says don't forget this Sutra is all
about Bodhisattvas
it's about carrying other people to
enlightenment and he says I'll tell you
one more thing are we here or where my
hands my hands what's it mean greater
way greater way then he says no it's not
the greater way it's the way for greater
people
okay got it
it's not maha Jana
it's Maha people like this Jana
okay people with big hearts go for this
one that's why we call it big way bigger
way okay it's because big people are
attracted to it
big hearted people big vision people
they like this Jana that's why we call
Mahayana those people who want to carry
other people on their shoulders who
agreed to do that
those are big people and the path they
follow is big pack Mahayana okay by the
way technically this is part of the
praising part he's like you are so cool
I will carry you okay you are if you do
meditation and integrate it into a
normal life you are worthy of my praise
I hold you up okay hmm then commonly she
was like bothered he saw I don't get it
Buddha said immeasurable good karma
immeasurable since then he says I
decided what it is if you hired all the
beings in the universe and they work
together to measure this karma you give
anyone a ruler
you know you get billion billion billion
people ruler and say measure this karma
even if they work together they can't do
it that's all
okay the Karma's to be all right I know
you're tired I am too but it's easier to
talk than to sit huh what's the next how
many more we got mmm you got one more
well we got a few more okay what's the
next picture members only only VIPs okay
then there's a weird explanations family
wrote me an email
what's it mean geshe-la omniscience of
exclusion exclusion means you don't let
other people come in that's exclusion
VIP lounge at the airport only if you
know doctor will can you come in I
learned that I go to the VIP lounge they
say you are you I use the idea I said no
but I know doctor welcome come on come
on okay so what's it mean Berta said
this Sutra is not for lesser people he
said that in the Sutra he says this
citrus not for lesser people this Sutra
I designed it for Bodhisattvas and other
people cannot come into this room while
I'm teaching it it's like Kamla Sheela a
diamond okay
we're kind of strict about people who
come into this class okay which is
another reason why you have to teach
when you get home because people cannot
come to community love for which is the
coolest one unless they come to the
first three so you have to teach them
okay so I like meeting you guys okay you
got to help people get ready okay turns
on
so somebody comes up to come with you
and since I have a question this is what
they say so Buddha is prejudiced right
like Buddha plays favorites if you're
Mahayana you can come to my clan if
you're not you can okay and in my
opinion then he's not a Buddha but I
should love everybody equally okay but I
should invite everybody to the class why
Buddha says only buddy stuffers can come
to this class it seems like a non
Buddhist thing to do it proves he's not
a real enlightened being okay somebody
makes a complaint they send a complaint
to the airport authorities you know why
you only let some people come in the VIP
lounge
you are not Buddhist you guys must not
be Buddhist okay got it okay because
he's not free of when he can't prejudice
he has prejudice you can come you cannot
I'll contraire on the contrary is that
right I don't know if I spelled it right
I just popped into my head may I have a
French name in there somewhere
Camila Sheila says the fact that Lord
Buddha excludes some people from this
teaching proof he's omniscient prove he
knows everything
because only a fool will try to teach
the same teaching to different peoples
levels okay only a non omniscient person
only a non Buddha will say everybody
come I'm going to explain deepest kamila
Sheila okay because half of them will
leave the next morning quietly guess
Allah has stomaching it's not my mom's
call me I have to go home okay got it
if he's omniscient
he will say if you're not a buddy
Sanford don't come to this class okay if
he's not omniscient he'll say everybody
coming and half the people will leave
because they're confused okay it means
when you teach check your audience
check your audience what's their level
be sensitive to your audience it's very
typical a DCI teacher a CI teacher they
will prepare twenty pages of complicated
notes you know and then they'll go to
the class and everybody's new and
they're like but my notes are so cool
they will understand anything but I
spent so long and make this then you
they just go ahead they teach it anyway
and people don't come back nobody comes
back okay like I don't know why ten
people came to my class second time only
three maybe there's a good movie out no
you you you taught the wrong level okay
they weren't ready for it so it often
happens to me you know this guy level
seven level eight the first level in I
cut like 75% out I said this is too much
you know people can't handle it you know
I just cut it okay so you have to have
that skill or you're going to teach
level one you know and then all these
people come and they're ready for level
two or they're letting ready for level
five teach level 5 it's ok ok sit the
audience if you don't you're not a
Buddha okay all right then master Camila
Sheila saris people with a lower
motivation right who are not ready to
carry other people if they come to this
diamond cutter teaching when Buddha
asked them not to okay
they will not be able to hear it okay
they will not be able to hear it
jesus said many many times if you have
ears listen then people said why do you
keep saying that he says some people
aren't ready for it then Matthew koma
Sheila says what does it mean when you
say that cannot hear it means they
cannot understand it and more
importantly they cannot use it in their
real life they can't use it in their
family you can't use it in their work
okay
those people are shouldn't be in the
class what you teach they cannot use it
it means they cannot hear means they
cannot use it okay they don't understand
it and they can't use it okay then come
along Sheila says by the way if you're
in this class if you heard the diamond
cutter Sutra if an omniscient being who
can see 2017 in 500 BC gave you a copy
the suture this morning you must be cool
[Laughter]
[Music]
you must be someone who can carry people
otherwise the surgery wouldn't come to
you okay you wouldn't get the suture
Nicole would give Nicole drive to Tucson
yeah where I know you did you do the
dirty work or who did it you did the
dirty work
let's take Nicole yeah
[Applause]
[Music]
it's like a four-hour trip to pick up
your dish now why don't you build a
retreat center next to Tucson I
we built two retreats out of here so you
can't get to Tucson okay here all right
so actually comma Sheila says Lord
Buddha is praising you guys implied
praising you you know if you made it
here you must be the kind of person who
likes to carry other people okay what
does it look like to carry other people
this came up in DC I you know we have
DCI teachers we take them on DCI tour
right they that this is a new DCI
teacher you know they say can you come
on the tour to say oh yeah I'm ready I'm
ready then you get to the airport you
said carry those 20 bags over there and
they're like no I'm a teacher you know I
came on the tour to teach you know and
you're like yeah that's what teachers do
they carry the luggage
you don't understand they're like no I
just want to teach big groups of people
yeah but a DCI teacher we got to start
that Scott we can go like this you know
you have to carry people being
Bodhisattva is not all about teaching in
front of large groups of people okay
getting red envelopes everyone writes
your poem you are so cool geshe-la
there's more luggage carrying than
teaching okay there's more cord wrapping
up than luggage carrying okay there's
more cleaning rooms thin cord wrapping
up
okay right
those of you been on a tour it can be
Jenny you know they said gage now I'm
ready I said okay here's 12 suits iron
them in five minutes they're like no no
I mean I'm ready to teach that's part of
teaching okay that's a big part of
teaching so a bodhisattva teacher just
getting into dirty work I said toilets
here okay
like Rinpoche was really big on teaching
me how to clean a toilet
he spent I don't know a couple years
teaching me to clean toilet that's not
clean Rinpoche it's better than my mom
used to do I don't care it's not clean
cleaning some more you know I cooked the
countless hours in ribbon I was to cook
for eight years he said let's have a
hundred people over for most I'm like no
please no I want to study diamond cutter
Center yeah this is diamond cutter
suture get used to it you know do you
know how long it takes to make 500
mumbles you know he would invite all the
Mongolians to dinner they they can eat
they like to eat I'm just like they're
like Momo Momo Momo Momo is there what
do you call the outfit making those
little dim sum like that it takes a long
time anyway so I just want to say this
section what is it 94 some again 92 it's
all about real bodies real Bodhisattva
way of life cleaning toilets raising
money you know washing machines you know
fixing the cars it goes together okay
don't be a princess Bodhisattva okay we
fired all the DCI princess Bodhisattvas
I remember one I'm not going to say her
name
might even be a boy but we're like carry
that suitcase she's like she like she
looked like the suitcase has some kind
of disease on it
she's like what carry that suitcase over
there no guitar I'm a teacher I said
yeah that's what teachers do they carry
suitcase all right and sometimes you're
tired and you get up and you carry
suitcases okay sometimes you don't feel
like it you're tired okay that's okay
don't hurt yourself I mean don't it's
important to get some sleep right Scott
I asked God did you sleep last night he
says I slept really fast guys know it
gets important to take care of how but
buddy saw me just give me more give me
more you know I can handle it
I'm Mahayana okay give me the dirty word
it goes together okay you will never be
a great teacher if you can't clean a
toilet you will never be a great teacher
if you can't wash the dishes okay
and if you leave dirty dishes for
somebody else to wash you're not a great
teacher either okay that's why all our
great teachers work in the kitchen after
they graduated from three-year retreat
okay right okay did you wonder about it
by the way one day when I was kvetching
anybody it's a Jewish word convent's
it's complaining
it's a reputation like wash those dishes
I'm like OMG I want to study down
consider is it Duncan assistants okay
then I said I'm going to time it how
long does it take to wash a big pile of
dishes it was six minutes okay all those
jobs you think are dirty and hard you're
just lazy you know they're not dirty and
hard you're just lazy
six minutes come on you spend that much
time in the bathroom with your science
fiction novels
or more all right let's see where are we
okay last one for today very sexy in
this section five things will happen to
you if you integrate your meditation and
your retreats into real life with your
family and your work okay what was the
fifth one what was the last one all
right what yeah it cleans away your old
bad scenes this is a very very famous
part of the diamond cutter future okay
those people who studied DCI you know
this part of the diamond cutter Sutra
okay the word old often gets attached to
Bad Seeds
because you're so nice now okay the bad
seed you collected in the past people
ask me good luck when did you make your
worst age when I was 16 that 16th
birthday to 17th birthday I made 90% of
my bad C's in one year I remember okay
can you remove those bad seeds no that's
a law of karma okay
it's the third law of karma if you don't
do something you don't get a result if
you do do something you don't get a
result you can't stop it okay if you
give away money money's going to change
you you can escape if you hurt somebody
problems are going to follow you you
can't escape they say like your shadow
it's like asking your shadow not to be a
shadow don't stop doing a shadow don't
do that
got it don't show a shadow there I don't
like it okay but you made the Karma you
will get the bad news on
you can pull out the wires of the bomb
okay I like I always tell people a story
about there's a very poor movie by John
Travolta called Broken Arrow it's a
really bad movie don't watch it but
there's one part I just can't forget
he's deep down in a salt mine he's
trying to pull the wires out of a
nuclear bomb and he sits on it with his
legs on either side if you're a boy you
know what I'm talking about he's
straddling a nuclear weapon like can't
he just sit on the side you know he's
got this thing up close to his important
stuff and he's pulling wires down it's
like I hope this is a wire you know you
know what happened he survived to make
another bad movie maybe it would have
been better if he blew up but anyway he
didn't carry the bomb and throw it in
the ocean
okay he didn't destroy the bomb he did
pull out the wires okay and that's what
we're doing when we do the four powers
okay when you do a proper confession
purifications
you don't destroy the bomb the bomb
stays inside you but it will never blow
up okay karmak all the comics feeds
billions billions billions in your mind
sit on the top of a needle you don't
have to worry about one more is in there
that's going to be there forever okay
that the bad seed will be there that's a
law of karma but you can fool around
with it okay when you fool around with a
bad seed it opens too early okay that's
how you get rid of your bad seeds you
don't really get rid of them okay
if I have a watermelon see Chico out
Jones she caught the Johnson and I put
it on my table here and I soaked it with
a wet paper towel
it will open too early and it will die
within an hour or three hours it cannot
survive in that environment it's
supposed to be in the ground
okay what's the environment that a seed
needs to survive you have to
misunderstand your husband
that's the soil that's the fertilizer
that's the sunlight the seed cannot
survive in a mine which understands
husband okay that negative seed your
husband yelling cannot survive if you
start understanding he comes from you
okay seed cannot live in a bad
environment called wisdom okay
it will open too soon then what happens
yeah you get a headache you were
supposed to get cancer but you got a
headache okay was the law of karma
respected did something bad come to the
person who did something bad yes but
it's sure better than cancer okay so
here we go last meditation to me oh it's
a booty section 95 any son or daughter
of noble family what's that code word
for male or female Bodhisattva okay who
takes up a suture like this or holds it
or region or comprehends it they will
suffer they will suffer intensely okay
why the seeds will open too early
because they their inner mind of wisdom
which is a hostile environment trusting
for bad seed okay cannot survive there
it'll open and it will die okay so we
heard many stories you know you have a I
like to tell the story I I taught the
diamond cutter sitter for many years and
one lady was driving in her car she
bought a CD of me teaching diamond
cutter Sutra she was listening to it in
her Volkswagen van driving down
California Highway she got to this Park
and the and the van started to burn it
caught on fire and she jumped out and
then it goes and she wrote me she said I
have two things to tell you this not
number one it worked you know my car
caught on fire
I'm so happy you know I said what's the
second thing she said can you send me a
new CD the old one melted
something small bad thing will happen
I'll tell you an important question
people ask me so how do I know when the
headache is just a plain old bad scene
or the headache is I'm pure fiying
a cancer scene like is there difference
between the two headaches the answer is
yes okay
after the heading okay after the
headache if you feel some very unusual
lightness like you just lost 15 pounds
okay and you just feel like yoga slide
talking cheapest light work is easy
family smooth then then the headache was
a purification okay if you if the
headache finish and you still feel bad
it's by just a normal bad sister
okay so you will feel light
okay and and it's the lightness of a
person who clean their bad C's okay and
you feel it also when you confess when
you open your heart to somebody okay I
used to I had a deal with myself I'm
gonna tell him I had a bad habit and
then I told I told myself I'm gonna tell
remember - anytime I haven't you know so
first time I went out I said remember
Terry this happened you know he said
that's disgusting
I'm like yeah I know I'm sorry he said
uh just terrible get out you know I'm
like thanks you know and then but I went
downstairs and I felt so light I felt so
happy you know I got rid of mine I told
a lot of the worst and then two weeks
later I open his door I'm like mama he
says I know get out okay okay but you
feel so happy when you clean up see okay
you feel like okay that's a sign
non-fatal headache okay
it means you didn't get cancer and you
got a headache okay now caramel uh
Sheila says yeah you will get headaches
you will get your car to catch on fire
etc etc but most common very common
people will criticize you for being a
Buddhist or people will criticize you
for your beliefs
okay he said that's one of the most
common openings of a negative speed okay
people say why why you why you go to
Diamond where you waste your time you
know you're so stupid
you know this whole idea seed seed seed
get real you know go to work work harder
stop giving away money you give I used
to give away half my income but I had to
deal with my company they will give away
the money that way I don't have to pay
tax and then the boss liked it because
they get
break so every six months I will get I
will go to the accountant CFO and and
and I will say okay it's time to cut to
check you say how much I said like I
don't know fifty thousand then he'll
make a check then I will take it to the
boss they'll sign it I'll give to the
donate to the John Brady or something
like that
exactly so one day the account CFO he
said he said mr. world you know sit down
I said yeah okay he said all right you
know this is nice you're giving away
money that's that's a nice thing you
know that's a good thing but it's kind
of stupid you know you you gotta have a
401k you ask our retirement plan
you can't work forever you're gonna get
old someday then you don't have any
money you know be reasonable you know
put some money in the bank I said god
damn it I did put it in the bank
I put it in a comma bang you know the
other banks can fail comma Bank never
fail you know I'm putting my money in
the safe place okay so you will be
criticized people will talk about you
you know oh she she that llama take
advantage of her you know she came home
with without much un you know you
endless she came home without much money
that llama made her luggage much lighter
yeah
they will take advantage stupid okay
then that's common ripening early
ripening or worse he says suffer
intensely means right the end of the
citruses you will suffer not just suffer
you will suffer intensely means maybe
people kill you or maybe old people put
you in jail for what you believe okay
then don't freak out
okay you you will get heavy criticism if
you follow this path that's what Kamla
Shima says okay Jesus said something
similar right blessed are they which are
persecuted for righteousness sake for
theirs is the kingdom of heaven blessed
are you when men shall revile you and
persecute you and shall say all manner
of evil against you falsely for my sake
rejoice be glad like that okay be happy
oh I I must be practicing people are
criticizing me but I think it's
important to say that if someone's
criticizing you because you're doing
something bad that's not the same thing
you are
hurting people stealing money you know
hurting your students and people
criticize you you shouldn't hide behind
the sutra you say oh that's just my
karma you know I must be practicing
really good I'm getting so much
criticism not nice okay in English we
say a grain of truth small piece of
truth in most criticism okay when when
people criticize you you know usually
there's if your wife criticize you
1% truth if your friends criticize you
2% truth but there's always some percent
truth okay oftentimes okay so when
you're criticized don't hide behind this
verse don't say Oh Buddha said I must be
really good diamond cutter person
because I got many criticisms don't
don't think like that
I think people criticize me there must
be something I'm doing wrong okay I I
will try to find it I'll try to stop it
okay like that so people criticize you
they help you if you don't have any
criticism you huh you have a problem
okay they help you identify your your
weaknesses in your fonts okay all right
last thing master Kamla Sheila says the
vacuum that's left when a bad karma
opens early is the best place for the
season enlightenment okay I'll say it
again the vacuum the empty space that's
left inside of you when you get that
headache and the headaches gone and
suddenly there's an empty space inside
of you the Bad Seeds gone you purify it
with egg hunting then there's some kind
of empty space in you that's the best
place to put a good seed for
enlightenment okay purify a bad thing it
leaves a space the seeds gone and
there's a space you know Gelson knows
there's some kinds of weeds in your
garden big ones
cheatgrass it's called cheatgrass you
have big one in front of your door it's
got those those many seeds on the end of
the stem
it's called cheatgrass it means it looks
like nice grass but later it just chokes
everything so anyway when you pull those
kind of wheat up it makes a really nice
hole for putting a new plant okay some
weed you have to fight them there's one
no you just pop it goes book and there's
a perfect hole to put a good see you see
you need you don't have to dig you just
pull out the weed and then there's this
beautiful little round hole just the
right yep put the good seed there cover
it okay
same with diamond cutter purification
okay when you get your headache when
your car burns up you have a space in
your life
and that's the best place to put a good
seat okay then do something cool okay do
something good and that's who will go
faster in the in the sadness left when
you when you destroy that dude okay
there's still some kind of flavor right
you still feel a little bit Sun about
the whole thing but that space is a good
space that's like good seas okay the
space of purification okay all right I'm
happy to say you're on track we can
finish complex you know three tomorrow
[Applause]